<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The art of memory so far forth as it dependeth vpon places and idea's[sic] Written first in Latine, by Iohn Willis Bachelour in Diuinitie: and now published in English by the said author, with such alternations thereof as seemed needful.</title>
            <title>Mnemonica, sive reminiscendi ars. Book 3. English</title>
            <author>Willis, John, d. 1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25749</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105364</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841093</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841093</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5652</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5652)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 945:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The art of memory so far forth as it dependeth vpon places and idea's[sic] Written first in Latine, by Iohn Willis Bachelour in Diuinitie: and now published in English by the said author, with such alternations thereof as seemed needful.</title>
                  <title>Mnemonica, sive reminiscendi ars. Book 3. English</title>
                  <author>Willis, John, d. 1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Iones, and are to be sold by Henry Seely in Pauls churchyard at the Tygres head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An English translation, with revisions, of the third book of John Willis' Mnemonica, sive reminiscendi ars.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The art of memorie.</note>
                  <note>Some leaves tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mnemonics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5652:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5652:1"/>
            <p>THE ART OF MEMORY, So far forth as it dependeth <hi>vpon Places and Idea's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written firſt in Latine, by <hi>Iohn Willis</hi> Bachelour in Diuinitie: and now publiſhed in Engliſh by the ſaid Author, with ſuch alterations thereof as ſeemed needful.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vt vnaquaeque ars nobiliſſima ac Diuiniſſima fuit: ita ad mortalium cognitionem tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſime pervenit.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Cardanus.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Iones,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Henry Seely</hi> in Pauls churchyard at the Tygres head 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5652:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5652:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas about ſome two or three yeares ſince, I publiſhed a Tractate in Latine called <hi>Mnemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a,</hi> concerning the Art of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie: diuided into three bookes, according to the threefold kindes of Artificiall remembring, that are therein preſcribed; and haue beene ſince importuned by diuers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o publiſh it in Engliſh: I haue anſwered their requeſt, ſo farre as I iudged it fit, by publiſhing the third booke thereof, which is
<pb facs="tcp:5652:3"/> plaine and eaſie for any mans vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; whereas the two firſt bookes are for Schollers onely, that are skilfull in Logicke and Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Yet haue I not tyed my ſelfe to ſuch ſtrict lawes as a Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſhould, but haue altered where I thought good, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, examples, and method<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thereof, with all libertie, to make it the more eaſie for the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the common ſort Writings (I confeſſe) are ſimply the moſt happie keepers of any thing in memorie, and doth for ſpeed and certaintie go beyon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any art of Memorie: but a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cannot alwayes write that which commeth into his minde, (as when he is riding vpon a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or lyeth awake in his bed, or is among companie at dinner, or in a throng of people, or is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:5652:3"/> hindered by any the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion) therefore it will be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for him then, to helpe his memorie ſome other way, at leaſt till he can ſet downe that in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which he would remember. And to this purpoſe ſerueth this Art; which if you ſhall aduiſedly reade through, and marke with diligence the precepts and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that you may well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand euery Chapter, as you go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, without haſtening to the end, before you come to it by due order, (like a man that would leape ouer a ſtile before he comes at it) I doubt not but you ſhall finde it very plaine and eaſie, and exceeding profitable for remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance both of buſineſſes and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations, and no way hurtfull to the facultie of the naturall memorie; but rather very vſefull
<pb facs="tcp:5652:4"/> for the corroboration and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening thereof. For the memorie being daily accuſtomed to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calling of ſentences forgotten, and that by one or two words thereof, (as this booke directeth) is thereby much quickned in her dutie, and the wit the more ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened. For nothing requireth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall exerciſe more then the memorie: neither is there any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie that waxeth ſooner dull for want of exerciſe, then the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie. This one thing I deſire to be fauourably cenſured, that if in the examples which I giue for the illuſtration of the practiſe of this Art in the fourteenth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, there appeare ought to be phantaſticall, it may be excuſed by this reaſon, that in this Art I go about to inſtruct the phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie, which is the ſeruant of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie.
<pb facs="tcp:5652:4"/> In which reſpect it fitteth well, that I deliuer ſome conceits which are phantaſticall. And thus haue I ventured to put theſe my labours vpon common conſtruction, hoping they ſhall finde no leſſe fauourable accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among the iudicious, then the Art of Stenographie, which long ſince I publiſhed, hath found.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:5652:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5652:5"/>
            <head>THE ART OF MEMORIE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Repoſitorie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Art of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, ſo farre foorth as it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth vpon Places &amp; Idea's, conſiſteth of two parts: <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> and <hi>Depoſition. Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> is that part, whereby things to be remembred, are layd vp in minde by their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea's,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5652:6"/> beſtowed in the places of <hi>Repoſitories.</hi> But before I come to the maner of beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or laying vp Idea's in the places of <hi>Repoſitories,</hi> neceſſary it is that I ſhould ſeuerally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate, firſt concerning <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitories;</hi> ſecondly the places therein determined; and third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touching Idea's in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces beſtowed.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> is an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary houſe or building, the forme and faſhion whereof is as followeth: Let there be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed a building of the beſt Cane ſtone to ſtand before vs, the inſide whereof is in length twelue yards, in bredth ſixe yards, &amp; in height ſeuen yards, and the roofe thereof flat, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded aboue, and pargetted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath, hauing no wall at all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5652:6"/> vpon the hither ſide which is towards vs, but the whole houſe lying wide open to our view. Let there be alſo ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed within the ſayd building, a marble ſtage ſmoothe and euen, one yard high aboue the leuell of the ground, whereon we ſtand; extending it ſelfe the full length and bredth of the ſaid building. And that all the three walls of the houſe (that is to ſay, the oppoſite wall, and the two ſide walls) are wholy lined on the inſide with choice cypreſſe boords, plaine and ſmoothe, and ſo cloſe ioyned, that it beareth no mention thereof to be ſeene, vnto a man ſtanding vpon this ſide of the ſtage. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, let there be imagined a grooue or gutter to be cut
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5652:7"/> in the iuſt middle of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtage, three inches deepe, and three inches broade, drawne from the oppoſite wall to the hither ſide of the ſtage, whereby it is exactly diuided into two equall parts: And that vpon the further end of the ſaid gutter, there is erected a <hi>Corinthian</hi> or round pillar, one foote and an halfe thicke, ariſing vp to the roofe of the building, which almoſt tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the oppoſite wall, and deuideth it exactly into two e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall parts; as the grooue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth the ſtage. So that by the grooue &amp; the pillar the whole <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> is parted in twaine, and conſiſteth of two roomes ſiding each other, and being each of them ſix yards long, and ſix yards broad, and ſix
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5652:7"/> yards high. But that you may the better perceiue this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, behold here the type and faſhion of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitorie,</hi> limited by the letters contained therein; whoſe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification followeth after the Figure.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:5652:8"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>plan of a repository</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:5652:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>a b</hi> ſheweth the length of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Repoſitorie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>a c</hi> and <hi>b d</hi> the height there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>a e</hi> and <hi>b f</hi> the height of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>e g h f</hi> the length &amp; bredth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſtage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>c l m d</hi> the length &amp; bredth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the roofe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>g i k h</hi> the length &amp; height <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the oppoſite wall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>e c i g</hi> the ſide wall vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ft hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>h k d f</hi> the ſide wall vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur right hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>g i n o</hi> the wall belonging to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e firſt roome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>c g o p</hi> the ſtage of the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>r q k h</hi> the wall of the ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>s r h f</hi> the ſtage of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5652:9"/> roome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>n o</hi> the pillar diuiding t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> oppoſite wall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>o p</hi> the grooue wrought in the ſtage.</p>
               <p>And ſuch a faſhioned <hi>Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitorie</hi> are we to prefixe befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the eyes of our mind, as oft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as we intend to commit thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to memory, ſuppoſing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelues to be right againſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> midſt thereof, and in the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance of two yards ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from.</p>
               <p>Now although euery <hi>Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitorie</hi> which we feigne to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before vs, muſt be of the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faſhion and building; yet a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they to be diſtinguiſhed on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from another, by the ſeueral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> colours of their pillars. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there are eighteene <hi>Repoſitori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in all, which are thus diſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guiſhed:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5652:9"/> The pillar of the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of gold; the pillar of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ond of ſiluer: both of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery bright and poliſhed. The pillars of the next ſeuen, muſt be ſuppoſed to be euery of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem of one entire ſtone ſmooth and ſhining, and thus d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>renced one from another. The colour of the pillar in the third <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> muſt be black; in the fourth <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> blue; in the fift, red; in the ſixt, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; in the ſeuenth, greene; in in the eighth, purple; in the ninth, white: ſo that theſe firſt nine <hi>Repoſitories</hi> haue but one pillar apiece in them; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nine are ſuppoſed to haue two, ſtanding together, in the middle of the <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> cloſe to the oppoſite wall; the one vpon the one ſide of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5652:10"/> grooue, and the other vpon the other ſide thereof, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing each other, and the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite wall with their baſes, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſified one from another, by a repetition of the nine former colours in the ſame order. For both the pillars in the tenth houſe or <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> muſt be imagined to be of gold: both pillars in the eleuenth houſe, of ſiluer; in the twelfth houſe of two entire blacke ſtones ſmooth and ſhining; in the thirteenth of two entire blue ſtones: and ſo likewiſe in the reſt. And thus much concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Repoſitories</hi> or imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary houſes, and how they are diſtinguiſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:5652:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of Places.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Place (as it is conſidered in this Art) is a roome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etermined in the <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for receiuing the Idea's or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ormes of things thereinto. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uery <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> are two places <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r rooms, and no more: which reſeuered each from other, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he grooue and pillar, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to the manner preſcribed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the former Chapter. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l that ſpace, which occupieth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he whole halfe part of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſitorie</hi> vpon the left hand, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounted the firſt place thereof: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd all that ſpace of the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alfe part of the <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the right hand, is counted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5652:11"/> the ſecond place. And ſo muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> concerning the places.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of Idea's in generall.</head>
               <p>AN Idea is a viſible repre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſentation of ought to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> remembred, beſtowed by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Imagination in one of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> places of a <hi>Repoſitarie,</hi> by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> remembrance whereof we ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to mind that which was there by ſignified.</p>
               <p>Euery Idea is to be accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panied with its proper circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtances, as the nature thereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doth require. For as any wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting, the fairer it is written the better it is read: ſo by ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> much the more liuely the Idea'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are ſet foorth, according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5652:11"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> exigence of their nature, much the ſooner are they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to mind, and by them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> things alſo committed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mory. Therefore to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s of things moouing, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſame motion is to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bed; and to the Idea's of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngs giuing a ſound, that ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſound is to be attributed. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amples of Idea's whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> motion is aſcribed, are, an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ificer at worke in his ſhop, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n and women dancing, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> running from a ſpout, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch like. Examples of Idea's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hereunto ſound is giuen, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion roaring, a Faulkner lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g, a bell ringing, a Quiriſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ging, a noice of Muſicians, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the like. Finally, euery I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ought to haue ſuch ſetting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, as ſeemeth in ſpeciall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5652:12"/> appropriated thereun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that it may be the better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> prehended by the memory.</p>
               <p>In euery Idea we haue fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things to be conſidered. Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titie, Poſition, Colour, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Kinde. Of which foure I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> intreate in their order.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Concerning the Quantitie of Idea's.</head>
               <p>AN Idea, in reſpect of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Quantitie, is either Equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Augmented, or Contracted.</p>
               <p>An Equall Idea is ſuch, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> whereby the thing to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> membred, being neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> great, but that it may be co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained in one of the places; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo ſmall, but being there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owed,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5652:12"/> it may eaſily be ſeene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one that ſtandeth two yards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this ſide the ſtage; is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re placed in its equall and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e quantitie. Of which ſort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a chaire, a table, a bedſteed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rniſhed, a heape of graine, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acke of wood, a duell fought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etweene two combatants, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the like.</p>
               <p>An Idea augmented, is ſuch, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> whereby the thing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>embred being ſo ſmall, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing it ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lfe alone beſtowed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one of the places of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſitorie,</hi> cannot be ſeen of him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at ſtandeth two yards in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de the ſtage, muſt therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e augmented by the increaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the number, of that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be placed. <hi>vt Quae non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt ſingula multa invent.</hi> As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r example: if the Idea to be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5652:13"/> beſtowed, be a pearle, a peni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a graine of muſtard ſeed, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſpider: theſe things are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> themſelues ſo ſmall, as bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſpoſed in one of the plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> they cann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be ſeene in the foremention<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſtance. Therefore for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pearle I ſuppoſe a buſhell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pearles to be heaped in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> middle of one of the places; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one pennie an heape of pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> new coyned; for one grai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of muſtard-ſeed, a coome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> muſtard-ſeed in like mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heaped together: for one ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, I ſuppoſe a multitude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpiders creeping cloſe togeth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the midſt of the oppoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wall.</p>
               <p>An Idea Contracted is ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as whereby the thing to be r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membred being ſo great, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:5652:13"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be contained in ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w limits, as the place of a <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>poſitorie</hi> is; is therefore ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed to be painted in liuely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lours, vpon that halfe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſite wall which belongeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the place wherein this Idea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be beſtowed. For all vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le things in the world, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough neuer ſo great, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſo farre diſterminate, may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry eaſily be repreſented by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cture drawne vpon the wall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this contracted forme. As if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thing to be remembred be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Church, a Citie, a mountaine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> comet, or other prodigious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gne in the heauen, a field <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ught, a fight at ſea, a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant paſſage in pomp &amp; ſtate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hunting or hawking through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſpacious forreſts, or any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>her the like, whoſe Idea in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5652:14"/> the full bigneſſe, cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> contained in a place of the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſitorie;</hi> All theſe are to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> foorth in a picture, occupyi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the one halfe of the oppoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wall, that in this attenuat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> form it maybe fully expreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> within the bounds and limi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of its proper place. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much concerning the Qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titie of Idea's: come we ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to their Poſition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Poſition of Idea's.</head>
               <p>LEt the poſition or ſitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of euery Idea be ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as is moſt agreeable to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing ſignified thereby. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe things which we co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monly hang vpon a wall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:5652:14"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ten thereunto, are here alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> like maner to be vſed. As if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Idea be ſome picture of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an; becauſe it is the vſe of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cture to be hung vpon a wal, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e muſt therefore ſuppoſe it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hang vpon the oppoſite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all: if it be a Proclamation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Title page of a booke, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is paſted vnto the wall; if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a new Pamphlet, that it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtned to the wall with nailes; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it be a Tombe, we muſt fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it to be ſet vp cloſe to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all, and the ſtreamers and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endants to be faſtened aloft <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto the oppoſite and ſide wall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the ſame roome, wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Idea is to be placed. So the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hings which are wont to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laced vpon a court-cupboord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſhelfe, are to haue like place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere: as a garniſh of plate, or veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5652:15"/> of glaſſe vpon a court c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boord; bookes or merce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wares beſtowed vpon ſhelue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Thoſe things which be acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtomed to be vpon tables, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> imagined here alſo to ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> place vpon a table: of whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſort are a banquet, moneys to out into ſeuerall heapes, pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing tables, &amp;c. Things plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon the ground, are here lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe ſuppoſed to haue pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon the marble ſtage, as a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, cheſt, cradle, or any liuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> creature ſtanding, ſitting, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing or lying along, &amp;c. Thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which are commonly and vſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally vnder ground, are here ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed to be vnder the ſtag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> For although they cannot b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeene of him that ſtandeth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this ſide the ſtage with his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dily eyes, yet they are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5652:15"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dden from the eyes of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind, which onely are exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in this Art. Examples of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is kind are a graue, a well, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine ſeller, a myne of gold, ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, lead, &amp;c. Finally, the ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me order is to be obſerued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſite and poſition of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther Idea's.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Colours of Idea's.</head>
               <p>COme we now to the third thing belonging to Idea's, which is Colour. Euery Idea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n what <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> ſoeuer it ſtandeth, muſt haue the colour of the ſame <hi>Repoſitory</hi> in whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or in part attributed vnto it. As if a blacke bull be to haue the place of an Idea in any of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5652:16"/> two roomes of the firſt <hi>Repoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie,</hi> the hornes thereof mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be ſuppoſed to be gilded; if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any place of the ſecond <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie,</hi> the hornes muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be tipt with ſiluer: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it be placed in the third <hi>Repoſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torie,</hi> the proper colour there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> being blacke already, is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of it ſelfe whereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the houſe wherein it ſtandeth. If he be beſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wed in the fourth <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> then le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him haue a garland of blue flowers about his necke; if in the fift <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> a garland of Damask roſes: if in the ſixt, of Marygolds: if in the ſeuenth, a w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eath of Bayes; if in the eight, of Cloue Iuly-flowers; if in the ninth, of Lillies.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, in attributing the colour of any <hi>Repoſitorie</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:5652:16"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> an Idea therein placed, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>articipating it of it ſelfe, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt haue a care that it be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lied as neare as we can to that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art which is moſt ſpectable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd conſpicuous. As if the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ry of <hi>Ionas</hi> the Prophet be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ainted vpon any halfe part of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he oppoſite wall in the firſt <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>epoſitorie,</hi> although therein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to be painted heauen, earth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a, land, a whale, a ſhip with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ariners in it; yet becauſe <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as</hi> being the ſubiect of the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ory, is the moſt ſpectable part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the picture, we may imagine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he hems of his vpper garment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be of gold: as we ſee it vſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rdinarily in pictures printed, wrought in diſtemper, and var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſhed. So if the picture of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as</hi> be an Idea in the ſecond <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> the hems of his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5652:17"/> may be ſiluered: if in the third <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> we may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine his vpper garment to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the colour of blacke; if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the fourth, of blue; if in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fift, of red, &amp;c. And thus much concerning the attribution o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the colour of the <hi>Repoſitories</hi> to the <hi>Idea's</hi> therein contained<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> come we now to the ſeueral kindes of Idea's.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of Direct Idea's.</head>
               <p>AN Idea is ſimple or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound. A ſimple Idea i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vniforme; and is either Direc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or Oblique.</p>
               <p>A Direct Idea is ſuch, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whereby a thing truly viſible, or conceiued vnder a viſible
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5652:17"/> forme, is layd vp in the ſame forme vnder which it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. So a goate is the direct Idea of a goate, a peacocke of a peacocke, a doue of a doue, a Church of a Church, a booke of a booke, &amp;c. So the Idea of any friend or acquaintance, is his true proper ſhape. So good and euil Angels, although they be ſpirits incorporeall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, yet ſince they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly conceiued vnder viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble formes, they are ſo to be expreſſed. Finally, of all things viſible, or conceiued vnder a viſible forme the mind it ſelfe doth preſently offer direct or right Idea's, that we ſhall not need to inuent any other, but to vſe them which are offered vnto vs. For if any ſhall make a narration vnto vs of a skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5652:18"/> at ſea, do we not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſe our ſelues to ſee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of our mind, the ſea ſhips, ſmoke of the gunnes diſcharged, &amp; ſuch like things as belong to a fight at ſea? If any ſpeake of muſtering and training men, do we not faſhion to our minds a certaine forme of a field, wherein ſouldiers march after their colours in a military order? Neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s there ought elſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re preſcribed, then that which nature it ſelfe hath taught vs, ſauing that for our better taking hold vpon theſe naturall Ideas, we obſerue an artificiall order and manner in laying them vp in minde, that we may the ſooner find them. And ſo much for a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Idea.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:5652:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of Relatiue Idea's.</head>
               <p>AN oblique Idea is ſuch, as whereby the thing to be remembred, is obliquely or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly ſignified. An oblique Idea is threefold: Relatiue, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a l. or Scriptile.</p>
               <p>A Relatiue is a ſimple Idea, whereby the thing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, is expreſſed by his his Correlatiue; as, firſt, when the cauſe is ſignified by the effect: As when Melancholy is ſignified by a man very ſad, who hauing his armes wrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed vp, and his hatt pull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d downe in his eyes, goeth vp and downe in a diſcontented manner. The Spring time, by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5652:19"/> the greene fields, and the trees putting forth their leaues. Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by the nakednes of trees, and the lakes and riuers frozen vp.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when the effect is ſignified by the cauſe. As if <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſignifie <hi>Oppreſſion of the poore,</hi> by a couetous miſer, who is euery where ill ſpoken of for his violence and extortion: or Blaſphemy, by a prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blaſphemous wretch well knowne vnto vs, all whoſe ſpeech is ſtuffed with dreadfull oathes and blaſphemies.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, when the Subiect is noted by the Adiunct: As when the Imperiall dignitie is ſignified by a Crowne and Scepter. A wine Tauerne by an ivy buſh and red lattice, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, when the Adiunct
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5652:19"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s noted by the Subiect: As when Cold is ſignified by ice; Heate by fire; Light by a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le; Affection by the heart, which is the ſeate of affections; Pride, by a Peacock; Gluttony <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y an Eſtrich; Drunkenneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y a drunken man; Impudence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y an harlot; Couetouſnes, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rich man with his bags about him, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, when the like is put for the like: As Parallel circles (that is, circles equally diſtant, including one another) for the world, becauſe the world con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of ſpheres, including one another, as parallell circles do. A woman holding a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken pillar, for Fortitude. A vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin hauing her eyes couered with a vaile, holding a ſword in one hand, and a paire of bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5652:20"/> in the other, for Iuſtice. An old man winged, hauing long haire in the forepart of his head, and being bald be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, for Time. And the like.</p>
               <p>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en a ſentence is expreſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a familiar exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whereby the truth of that ſentence is manifeſted: as, if this ſentence [<hi>Venter mero ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuans deſpumat in libidinem:</hi> that is, The belly ouer-heated with wine, doth froath forth into luſt,] ſhould be expreſſed by the example of <hi>Lot,</hi> ſporting with his daughters; in whoſe fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, this example was plainly verified.</p>
               <p>Finally, when any thing may fitly be reſembled by its cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relatiue, it muſt be ſo reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. And ſo much for Relatiue Idea's.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:5652:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of Subdititiall Idea's.</head>
               <p>A Subdititiall Idea is, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a proper name is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itted to memory, by ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing placed in ſtead there of, wherewith it is ſuppoſed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue ſome agreement. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> done two wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, when a mans name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnifieth ſomething viſible, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay be layd vp in memory by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat viſible thing it ſignifieth: As if a mans name be <hi>Smith,</hi> his name may be reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hinking vpon a Smith at work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n one of the roomes of the <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> hauing forge and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nvile in it, as if it were a Smiths ſhop: if his name be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5652:21"/> 
                  <hi>Carpenter,</hi> by a Carpenter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> worke: if <hi>Turner,</hi> by a Turne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if his name be <hi>Stone,</hi> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtone: if <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onne,</hi> by a Lute an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Tunne.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a mans name m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be remembred by the lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> name giuen to another ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> As if a mans name be <hi>Pete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> we may remember it by ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther man called <hi>Peter,</hi> or b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the picture of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon the oppoſite wall: if h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> name be <hi>Iohnſonne,</hi> by anothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man of the ſame name: if a w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mans name be <hi>Lucreſe,</hi> it ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be kept in mind by the pictur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Lucreſe:</hi> if <hi>Katharine,</hi> by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> picture of Saint <hi>Katharine.</hi> An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this may ſuffice for Subditia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Idea's.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:5652:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of Scriptile Idea's.</head>
               <p>A Scriptile Idea is, whereby the thing to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red, is ſuppoſed to be written <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n a plaine white table hanged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p in the midſt of the oppoſite wall belonging to the roome wherein it is placed, the frame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r border whereof is of oake, very broad and chamfered. In euery Scriptile Idea, 3 things are generally required.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the Table be not much bigger then will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that which ſhall be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the frame or border of the Table, be of the colour of the <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> wherin
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5652:22"/> it ſtandeth. As if it ſtand in the firſt <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> that it be of the colour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gold; if in the ſecond <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> that it be of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of ſiluer; if in the third, that it be black; if in the fourth, blue, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that the letters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scriptile Idea, be all of ſuch bigneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as that they may plainly be read by him that ſtandeth on this ſide of the <hi>Repoſitorie;</hi> like vnto the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings which we ſee in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. And thus much fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that which is generally required in all Scriptile Idea's. Let vs now ſee, what is further to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the ſeuerall kinds of them.</p>
               <p>There are foure kindes of Scriptile Idea's: A ſingle word, a Quotation, a Phraſe, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5652:22"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sentence.</p>
               <p>A ſingle word and quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, muſt be written in a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>let one foote and an halfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>road, and a foote high; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir firſt letter muſt be a great Romane capitall letter of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raordinary bigneſſe aboue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt, and the tranſcendencies of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſmall letters alſo, if there be any muſt be drawne much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igher or lower then is vſuall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n common writing. For by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his meanes they are the more eaſily attracted by the viſuall facultie, and transferred to the memory. By the tranſcenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the ſmal letters, I meane the vpper and lower parts of thoſe letters, which exceed the parallell lines betweene which we write. For whenſoeuer we write, we write, as it were, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5652:23"/> two lines vnderſtood, though not expreſſed. And of the ſmall letters, ſome are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wholy between the lines, as theſe, <hi>a c e m n o r s u v w,</hi> which for diſtinction ſake may be called Interlineals, becauſe they are written between the lines. All other ſmall letters are extended further then the lines, whereof they are called Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendents. And of theſe, ſome are extended aboue the vpper line, as theſe, <hi>b d h i k l t:</hi> ſome beneath the lower line, as theſe, <hi>g p q x y z.</hi> Some both aboue the vpper line and beneath the neather line, as theſe, <hi>f</hi> j <hi>ſ.</hi> As to giue examples in ſingle words: the word <hi>Canaan</hi> hath no tranſcendents in it; <hi>Naboth</hi> hath three, which extend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the vpper line, <hi>b t</hi> and <hi>h.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5652:23"/> Spagyrus</hi> three, which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rawne beneath the neather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, <hi>p g</hi> and <hi>y. Ioſaphat</hi> hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hree tranſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces aboue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pper line, in the letters <hi>ſ h</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and two beneath the lower <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, in the letters <hi>ſ</hi> and <hi>p.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When therefore we haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ancied a ſingle word to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ritten in a tablet hanging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon the oppoſite wall, we muſt apply our mind thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o impenſiuely to conſider it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd eſpecially the length of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he firſt letter, and the tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>encies of the ſmall letters if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here be any, till by theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the word make ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpreſſion of it ſelfe in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inds. That, whereas a word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arely written, is but feeble of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe to ſtir vp memory, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y theſe conſiderations and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5652:24"/> ſtay made in beſtowing it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may worke ſome deeper im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſion in our memories.</p>
               <p>A Quotation muſt be writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten after the common maner thus, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.8. And beſides the conſideratio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the firſt letter, and the tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcendences of the ſmall letters if there be any in it, we muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obſerue alſo the numbers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Chapter and verſe, but ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially of the Chapter; whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will be very eaſie to commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to mind, in regard of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quantitie. For things of quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, next things viſible, are be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> remembred.</p>
               <p>A phraſe and a ſhort ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence of one line in length muſt be ſuppoſed to be writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in a table three foot broa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and one foote high, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:5652:24"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hiefe word therein, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be accounted, that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt expreſſeth the ſubiect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ereof, (whether it ſtand in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e beginning, middle or end) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be written after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er of words written alone; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat is, the firſt letter to be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eat Romane capitall letter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the tranſcendencies of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>all letters therein very large.) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd when we haue once fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed a phraſe or ſhort ſentence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be written in the table, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt apply our ſelues to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>der the length of this whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>criptile Idea, ſpecially the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hiefe word therein, and what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace it hath in the writing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> whether in the beginning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iddle or end:) for by theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſiderations vſed in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſition of Scriptile Idea's,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5652:25"/> they are the better remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred.</p>
               <p>If a Scriptile Idea be a lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſentence, which cannot be co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained in a line, then let th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> table be imagined to be bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der or deeper, as the length <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Idea doth require. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> let the forme of writing, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> euery long Idea hath, be ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as may moſt plainly ſet foot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what kind of ſentence it do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> expreſſe. Therefore Diſtrib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions muſt be expreſſed by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> parts drawne to their whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with braces in this manner.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5652:25"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The feaſts of the Iewes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Sabbaths, were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>More ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne: to wit,</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>The Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Pentecoſt.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>The feaſt of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Leſſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne: to wit,</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>The feaſts of their new Moons.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>The feaſt of blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                                       <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>The feaſt of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piation.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>So Syllogiſmes are to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed into their Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, Aſſumption and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, as:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5652:26"/>
                  <list type="syllogism">
                     <item>
                        <hi>If the firſt matter of all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreall creatures be capable of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny forme; then though the bodies of all men were, diſſolued into their firſt matter, they may be reſtored to their proper forme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>But the firſt matter of all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreall creatures is capable of any forme:</hi> according to that Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophicall Axiome, <hi>Materia prima eſt omnium formarum ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptibilis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Therefore though the bodies of all men were diſſolued into their first matter, they may be reſtored to their proper forme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>So Obiections with their Anſwers, are to be diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this maner.</p>
               <div type="objection">
                  <head>Obiection.</head>
                  <p>Whatſouer euery man muſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5652:26"/> beleeue, is true. <hi>(For nothing falſe muſt be beleeued.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But euery wicked man muſt beleeue that he ſhall be ſaued by Chriſt. <hi>(For not to beleeue this is infidelitie, and therefore ſinne.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore euery wicked man muſt beleeue that he ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Euery wicked man muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that he ſhall be ſaued; yet not abſolutely, but vpon condition that he repent, and beleeue in Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Similitudes and all other compariſons both whoſe parts are explicated, are to haue thoſe parts ſiding one another in this ſort:
<list>
                           <item>As there is great difference
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5652:27"/> between the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of light and the act of ſeeing: (for the facultie is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes preſent with him that hath his ſight; but the act is often intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.)</item>
                           <item>So there is a great difference
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5652:27"/> between the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of faith and the act of beleeuing: (for the facultie of faith is alwayes in the Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate after their conuerſion; but the act of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.)</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>So verſes are to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by their ſeuerall lines: and generally all other kindes of ſentences which haue or may haue a peculiar kind of writing by it ſelfe, ought here in that maner to be written.</p>
                     <p>Furthermore, it is requiſite, that ouer a long Scriptile Idea, one or two of the chiefeſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5652:27"/> words be written in ſome little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſtance therefrom, as if it were the title of it, their firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>etter being a great Romane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>apitall, and the tranſcenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ies of the ſmall letters produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed in length, after the maner of words written alone. As to giue inſtance in the former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mples: ouer the firſt Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ile Idea, (which is a diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ion) theſe words muſt be written, <hi>Iewiſh Feaſts.</hi> Ouer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he ſecond, (which is a Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme) theſe, <hi>Firſt Matter.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er the third (which is an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ection with the ſolution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) theſe, <hi>Beleeue ſaluation.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the fourth, (which is a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude) theſe, <hi>Sight and Faith.</hi> And hauing in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits written any long Idea after this maner, we muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5652:28"/> our ſelues intenſiuely t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> conſider the length of the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence, the maner of writing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and the title thereof ouer i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> together with the firſt letter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and tranſcendences of the ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle, letting our mind to wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vpon theſe conſiderations fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a while, till the Idea be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſetled therein.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of compound Idea's.</head>
               <p>HAuing now gone tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough with all the ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple Idea's, I come to Idea'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that are compounded. A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound Idea, is compounde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of two ſimple Idea's; whereof the one is alwayes a Scriptil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Idea, and the other is either
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5652:28"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Direct Idea, or a Relatiue. A compound Idea therefore is of two ſorts.</p>
               <p>The firſt kind of compound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dea's, is of them which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt partly of a Direct Idea, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>artly of a Scriptile. Of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ort are, an hiſtory painted in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> faire table, with verſes vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ath explaining it; a libell or Epigramme, made vpon ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing done, ſuppoſed to be written in a paper, and paſted vpon the oppoſite wall, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he thing done expreſſed in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion vpon the ſtage; An armed Knight bearing his Scutcheon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd impreſe written therein; and the like.</p>
               <p>The ſecond kind of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound Idea's, is of them which conſiſt partly of a Relatiue I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea, and partly of a Scriptile.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:5652:29"/> Of this ſort are innumerable examples in Emblemes, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Beza, Alciat, Peacham,</hi> and others. For in all Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemes, the picture occupying the vpper part of the table, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Relatiue Idea; and that which is written vnderneath, a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile. And thus much for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound Ideas, and ſo concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all the ſeuerall kinde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Idea's.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the chooſing Idea's.</head>
               <p>IT is meet in the next place, to giue ſuch rules, whereby we may know at the firſt, with what Idea euery thing that is to be remembred, muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Touching which, theſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5652:29"/> ſix Rules following giue infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ible and certaine direction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 1. All hiſtories, things done, fables, common buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, finally whatſoeuer is viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or conceiued vnder a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble forme, and nor illuſtrated by ought written, ought to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayd vp in memory, by a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect Idea in equall quantitie, greater or leſſe, as the nature of the Idea requireth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 2. All hiſtories, things done, fables, morals, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke, explaned by verſes or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther writing: as alſo all Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grams, Epitaphs, Anagrams, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpreſes, and libels, are to be expreſſed by an Idea com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of a Direct Idea and a Scriptile.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 3. All Emblemes and ſentences exemplified by ſome
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5652:30"/> notable inſtance, are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by a compound Idea, conſiſting of a Relatiue and Scriptile Idea.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 4. All Charact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary letters, bare numbers, and quotations, are to be layd vp by a Scriptile Idea.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 5. All ſingle words and proper names, expreſſible by a Subditiall Idea, ought ſo to be expreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 6. All ſentences, phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, words or names which can not preſently be expreſſed by a Direct, a Relatiue, a Subditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, or a compound Idea, ought to be expreſſed by a Scriptile Idea. And this for the choice of Idea's ſhall ſuffice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:5652:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> Of the maner of beſtowing Idea's in their places.</head>
               <p>HItherunto I haue intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted concerning <hi>Repoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Places</hi> and <hi>Idea's</hi> ſeuerally. Now I come to the maner of beſtowing <hi>Ideas</hi> in the places of <hi>Repoſitories.</hi> Wherein theſe rules following are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 1. Euery <hi>Idea</hi> is to be placed in order: that is to ſay, that which commeth firſt to mind, in the firſt place of the firſt <hi>Repoſitorie:</hi> That which commeth next to mind, in the ſecond place of the firſt <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie;</hi> The third <hi>Idea</hi> in the firſt place of the ſecond <hi>Repoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie.</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:5652:31"/> The fourth, in the ſecond place thereof. The fift, in the firſt place of the third <hi>Repoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi> The ſixt, in the ſecond. And ſo forth in the reſt of the <hi>Repoſitories,</hi> how many ſoeuer they be: alwayes prouided, there be but one <hi>Idea</hi> aſſigned to one place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 2. Let due quantitie, poſition, and the colour of the <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> be rightly attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to euery <hi>Idea,</hi> and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued and marked, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereunto. For it can not well be told, how much help and furtherance theſe 3 attributions, ſpecially the aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the colour of the <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie</hi> to euery <hi>Idea,</hi> do bring to a deep imprinting in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, as well as the <hi>Idea's</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as alſo the order where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5652:31"/> they ſtand. For by this meanes the mind, when it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to repeate ouer the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea's,</hi> hath one thing certainly knowne to belong to euery <hi>Idea</hi> to worke vpon: that is to ſay, the colour of the <hi>Repoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> which in one reſpect or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he knoweth to be in the <hi>Idea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 3. After the ſecond <hi>Idea</hi> of any <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed in its proper place, let it be conſidered, whether by ſome proper fiction it may haue ſome fit connexion with the former <hi>Idea,</hi> ſtanding in the ſame <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> in reſpect of the action thereof, in ſome kind of maner affecting the former. As for example: ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that the <hi>Idea</hi> placed in the firſt room of the <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> be
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:5652:32"/> an old man ſleeping in a chair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the fire ſide; and that the <hi>Idea</hi> in the ſecond roome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> be a black S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith or Farriar giuing an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> horſe a drench: I fayn therfore, that the horſe ſtruggling and bounding vp with his fore feete, doth awake the old man ſitting by the fire in the former roome. And this relation is, as it were, a knitting or chaining of this <hi>Idea</hi> with the former: ſo that if we remember one of them, we cannot lightly be forgetfull of the other. If a fit relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be not preſently found, by transferring the action of the latter vnto the former; then let there be fought ſome other agreement, which the latter hath with the former: either in reſpect they do both concerne
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:5652:32"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſame ſubiect, (as when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubiect of them both is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning warre, peace, iuſtice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ne, patience &amp;c.) or ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, in reſpect they are both <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea's</hi> of the ſame kind, (as when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth of them are direct <hi>Idea's,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth Relatiues, both Subditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iall, both Scriptiles, or both compound <hi>Idea's.</hi>) And if they agree neither in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, nor in the kind of <hi>Idea,</hi> then we are to faſten vpon that relation, which they may haue in reſpect of their ſituation or poſition, by conſidering their poſition to be like, if it be like; (as when both <hi>Idea's</hi> are placed vpon the ſtage, both vpon a table, both vpon the oppoſite wall, &amp;c.) or different if they be of a different ſituation, (as when one hath place vpon the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:5652:33"/> ſtage, and the other vpon the wall:) for euen by this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, both <hi>Idea's</hi> are the better remembred.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 4. When the latter <hi>Idea</hi> of any <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> is beſtowed, we muſt repeate in our mind (if time will giue vs leaue) all the former <hi>Idea's</hi> of the other houſes. For as a ſcholler by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reading ouer his leſſon, getteth it without booke: ſo by often repeating theſe <hi>Idea's</hi> in our mind, we ſhall the better retaine them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 5. We muſt take hee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that we ouercharge not our memory with a multitude of <hi>Idea's:</hi> for as it is hurtfull to loade the ſtomack with more meat then it can digeſt at once; ſo is it alſo vnprofitable to oppreſſe the memory with too
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:5652:33"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat a multitude of <hi>Ideas.</hi> Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch obſeruations therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe as are common and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and let vs commit ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly to memory, as are indeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emorable. The number of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings that may be committed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> once vnto a mans memory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this Art, are ſix and thirty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich are abundantly ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t for the memory to be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed withall at once, and more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y many peraduenture then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhall haue occaſion at any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me to vſe. And ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erning the choice of <hi>Ideas,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd beſtowing them in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:5652:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> Concerning the practiſe of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Art of Memorie.</head>
               <p>IT remaineth that now at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I ſhould illuſtrate all the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer precepts of this Art by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> examples, that the vſe by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> practiſe thereof may be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> better ſeene. I will therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhew the vſe thereof: firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> remembring buſineſſes; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>condly in remembring obſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uations.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore concernin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> buſineſſes. Suppoſe that a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> riding alone towards a Fay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kept in ſome market Town for ſome eſpeciall buſineſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and that as he is vpon his iou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney, diuers other buſineſſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:5652:34"/> come into his mind there to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> done; he muſt then beſtow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, and lay them vp in order <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their places by their <hi>Idea's,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey come to mind. As for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mple.</p>
               <p>The firſt buſineſſe he thinks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, is to enquire the price <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeed wheat in the market. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him therefore ſuppoſe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> firſt place or roome of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> that he ſeeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers men ſtanding together <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h ſacks of corne, that it may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſome face of a corne mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; and that on the nearer ſide the ſtage, he ſeeth a country <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n clad in ruſſet, with a paire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> high ſhooes on, powring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eate out of a ſacke into a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhell, the eares or handles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ereof are of pure gold; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this ſuppoſition the <hi>Idea</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:5652:35"/> may haue the colour of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſitorie</hi> which is gold, attrib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted vnto it; according to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rule of the ſixt Chapter.</p>
               <p>The ſecond buſineſſe is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> procure mowers to cut do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> medow graſſe. Let theref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be ſuppoſed in the ſeco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> place of the firſt <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> or foure husbandly men to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> whetting their ſithes, the bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whereof are of gold, agreeab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the colour of the <hi>Repoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie;</hi> and that the ſound alſo whetting their ſithes is perfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly heard. The relation wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Idea hath vnto the form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is in reſpect of ſituation: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe both Idea's are pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon the ſtage of the firſt <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſitorie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third buſineſſe is, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quire out one whoſe name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:5652:35"/> 
                  <hi>Fletcher,</hi> dwelling in that owne, and vnknowne vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im. Let him therefore fancy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat the firſt part of the ſecond <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> is turned, as it were, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto a Fletchers ſhop, wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Fletcher ſtandeth cloſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ſtall, hauing a great box of ſiluer arrow heads by him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he is buſied in heading of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrowes. The fiction of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow heads to be of ſiluer, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth to attribute the colour of the <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea.</p>
               <p>The fourth buſineſſe is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uy pepper. For the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rance of this, the ſecond place of the ſecond <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> muſt be ſuppoſed to be changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the form of a Grocers ſhop. And that the oppoſite wall is ſet forth with a neſt of boxes,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:5652:36"/> whereupon the names of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are written, according to the common cuſtome of Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſhops, and the ſide wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo furniſhed with Grocery ware: and that two foote o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this ſide the oppoſite wall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is a Counter or a ſhew-boord and the Grocer ſtanding vpon the further ſide of it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a blue apron before him, is weighing of pepper in a pair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ballance, the ſcales whereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are ſiluer, (as is the pillar o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this <hi>Repoſitorie.</hi>) The relation of this Idea to the former, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in this, that both are ſhops: The firſt containing things ſaleable, that are prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for mens deſtruction; and this, ſuch things as whoſe vſe ſerueth for mens preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:5652:36"/>
               <p>The fift buſineſſe is to ſpeak with a Councellor. Let that Councellor then be imagined to ſit in a blacke gowne lined with veluet, in a chaire in the middeſt of the firſt place of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he third <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e turning ouer a booke of ſome mans caſe, which he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n his hand. Here needeth no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttribution of colour, ſince the Councellors gowne is blacke of it ſelfe, which is the proper colour of this <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> whoſe pillar is of ieat.</p>
               <p>The ſixt buſineſſe is to buy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yard of black veluet. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſecond roome of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hird <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> muſt be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ormed, as it were, into a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers ſhop, and vpon the ſhew-boord there muſt be ſuppoſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o lie a piece of blacke veluet
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:5652:37"/> open, the Mercer being on the other ſide thereof praiſing an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> commending it. This Idea hath alſo of it ſelfe the colour of the <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> as the former had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and may be referred vnto it by this imagination, that vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet (which is the ſubiect o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Idea) is alſo the facing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Lawyers gowne, which ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the former roome.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall not need to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed any further in giuing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples for remembrance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> buſineſſes, ſince their Idea'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the moſt part are D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rect and ſuch as nature it ſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> offers to our mind: I wil there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now proceed to giue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Obſeruations to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> remembred, and ſhew how their Idea's are to be beſtowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the <hi>Repoſitories</hi> following.</p>
               <div n="1" type="observation">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:5652:37"/>
                  <head>The firſt Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>Diogenes the Cynicke, when entred into Plato's hall, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the table therein couered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th a faire carpet, and the cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>rd to be furniſhed with plate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d the reſt of his houſhold ſtuffe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ptuous and rich: He pluckt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the carpet in a kind of indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion, and trampled vpon it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th his feete, ſaying; I ſpurne Plato's pride. Yea but (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>red Plato) with a greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>de.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition thereof.</head>
                     <p>The Idea of this <hi>Apoph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gme</hi> is direct, and not ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at, but that it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ned in one of the memoriall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ces, nor ſo ſmall, but being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rein placed, it may be dil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ned by one which ſtandeth this ſide of the ſtage: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:5652:38"/> I ſuppoſe the Idea to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> there layd vp in equall qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titie, according to the ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. by imagining the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> place of the fourth <hi>Repoſito<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> (whoſe colour is blue) to ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> both the oppoſite and ſide w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> hung with tapiſtry, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> cloſe vnto the oppoſite w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> there ſtandeth a cupboord plate; and in the middle of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> roome a faire table, couer with a carpet of blue ſilke; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> an old man with a long wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> beard, ſitting in a chaire by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſide wall, as maiſter of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> houſe, apparelled in an A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demicall habite, to repreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Plato</hi> the father of the <hi>Aca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>micks.</hi> And further, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> comes to the table ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> man in a patcht gowne, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> beggerly apparell, which p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:5652:38"/> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h off the carpet, and tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> it vnder his feete. Which <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ato</hi> beholding, riſeth out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> chaire, takes vp the carpet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d taxeth his rudeneſſe. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lour of the carpet is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le to the colour of the <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>orie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="observation">
                  <head>The ſecond Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aeterea, ſi nulla fuit generalis origo</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rrarum, &amp; Coeli, ſempérque aeterna fuêre,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r ſupra bellum Thebanum, &amp; funera Troja,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>on alias alij quoque res cecinê<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Poetae. Lucretius.</l>
                     </q> In Engliſh thus:
<q>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oreouer, if there neuer was of yore,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eginning of the world; but that it was</l>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:5652:39"/>
                        <l>Alwayes eternall: wherefore th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> before</l>
                        <l>The warres of Thebes and Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> did come to paſſe,</l>
                        <l>Did there no Poet write of oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> things?</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition thereof.</head>
                     <p>This is to be expreſſed by compound Idea, in this ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner. Imagine a faire large tab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> about fiue or ſix foote ſquar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to hang vpon the oppoſite w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of the ſecond roome in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> fourth Repoſitory; whoſe c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lour being blue, cauſeth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> frame of the table to be ſo to In the vpper part of the tab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> I ſuppoſe to be painted in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerall ſquares, diuided ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> from the other by a down right blue line 3 inches broa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the deſtruction of <hi>Thebes,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> the deſtruction of <hi>Troy,</hi> whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:5652:39"/> is a night piece: and that in the lower part of the table, thoſe foure verſes before mentioned of the Poet <hi>Lucretias,</hi> are fairly written. In this Idea the blue line of the partition is to be wel marked, becauſe it ſheweth the picture to conſiſt of ſeuerall hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories. The relation which this Idea hath to the former, is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from difference of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that whereas the former Idea of this Repoſitory hath place vpon the ſtage, this is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vpon the oppoſite wall.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="observation">
                  <head>The third Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>Euery thing which is iuſt, is not agreeable to equitie. For Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Torquatus did iuſtice, but not equitie, when he cauſed his valiant ſonne to be bebeaded; for
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:5652:40"/> that he, contrary to his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, being mightily prouoked by the inſolence of the enemie, had fought with them in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, although he returned with victorie.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>This is to be expreſſed by a direct Idea ſtanding in the firſt place of the fift Repoſitory, the colour of whoſe pillar is red. I fancie therefore to ſtand therein a big man in complete armour, his beauer vp, of a dreadful and aſtounding coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, hauing a plume of red feathers vpon his creſt, with a great chaine of gold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his necke, (bearing the ſignification of his name <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quatus</hi>) and reſting his right hand vpon a red truncheon applied to his ſide; he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:5652:40"/> earneſtly to commaund ſome of the ſouldiers in red coates by him, to haſten a yong man pinioned to execution.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="observation">
                  <head>The fourth Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>A man in ſome caſe may do dammage vnto his neighbour, though he know it, yet without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie. For if there be two victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſes together in a towne, the keeper of the one doth dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to the other, in as much as he ſeeketh to draw the gueſts to his houſe: yet is this dammage without iniurie, and therefore not puniſhable by any law of the land.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>The Idea of this is alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect in equall quantitie. For it is to be ſuppoſed, that in the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:5652:41"/> oppoſite wall of the ſecond place of the fifth <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> there is a doore opening into a victualling houſe, adioyning vnto the <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> on the back ſide, hauing a red lattice window, and railes before it: and that in the ſide wall vpon the right hand, there is a doore open, leading into another vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualling houſe, adioyning to the end of the <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a red lattice alſo before the window. Further, let there be imagined ſome common drunkard to ſit vpon a bench on this ſide the further Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, with a kan of ale in his hand; who looking into the former roome, and ſeeing <hi>Manlius</hi> his ſonne ready to be caried away to execution, pointeth to his kan, and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:5652:41"/> to vtter theſe words to <hi>Manlius</hi> his ſonne, as he ſeeth him to paſſe along by him: Oh this were good for thee now, if thou mighteſt ſit by it. For ſuch like idle conceits as this, will make a matter the better to ſticke in mind.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="observation">
                  <head>The fift Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>There is no excellent wit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome madneſſe.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>The Idea hereof is Relatiue, committed to memory, by ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing well knowne, to be in the firſt place of the ſixt <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie,</hi> who through too much intenſion of mind vpon his ſtudies, is fallen into a deepe phrenſie; and that he hauing a great yellow feather in his hat, rideth vp and downe the ſtage vpon an hobby-horſe.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="observation">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:5652:42"/>
                  <head>The ſixt Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>Ilia, called alſo Rhea, being great with child by Mars, had at a birth two children, Romus and Remus; whom ſhe deliuered to a notable harlot, called Lupa, to be by her nurced and brought vp: of whom all brothel-houſes were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter called in Latine, Lupanaria: (as the Engliſh word Harlot, was firſt deriued from Arletta, concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine of Robert Duke of Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, father of William the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror.) Hence grew that fable, that theſe twinne-borne brethren weee nurced by a ſhe wolfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Lupa in Latine ſignifieth a ſhe wolfe. Romus after being King, gaue name to Rome: but was called by the people, in a kind of flatterie, by the diminutiue of his name, Romulus.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:5652:42"/>
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>This is to be layd vp by a Direct Idea, ſuppoſing that in the ſecond place of the ſixt <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> there lyeth vpon a pad of ſtraw a ſhe wolfe, hauing about her necke a yellow col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, with two infants ſucking of her. And that the wolfe ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out her throate, howleth ſo deernly, that the franticke man in the former roome ſtops his dauncing to looke at her.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="observation">
                  <head>The ſeuenth Obſeruation.</head>
                  <q>
                     <p>Milo of Croton, a famous wreſtler, who was the firſt crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at Olympia, when being old be trauelled along through the woodland countries of Italie, eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an oake neere the way ſide, rif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the midſt. Then intending (as I thinke) to trie, whether as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:5652:43"/> yet there remained any ſtrength in his armes, thruſting his hands into the rift of the tree, he rent it downe a little way: but the oake being thus bowed, and drawne into two parts, cloſed againe vpon his hands, as he was ſtill tugging thereat, and held him there faſt, to become a prey to the wilde beaſts.</p> 
                     <bibl>Aul. Gellius Attic. Noct. <hi>15. 16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>The Idea of this obſeruation is a Direct Idea, and muſt be placed in the firſt roome of the ſeuenth <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> the colour whereof is greene. I ſuppoſe therefore a young oake with greene leaues: and acornes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, to grow vp out of the middle of the ſtage, being rif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the midſt: and that a big man, broade ſhouldered,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:5652:43"/> and apparelled like a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, after the ancient guize, with a garland of greene law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ell vpon his head, hath both his hands in ſuch manner inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the oake, who caſting backe his head and body, cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth aloud for help; ſo that me thinks, I ſee not onely the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backe of his body, and his ſtriuing to get looſe, but euen to heare with mine eares the outcrie which he maketh.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="observation">
                  <head>The eight obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>To driue forward the night with old wiues fables.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>This Phraſe may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to mind by a Direct I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea, in this manner. Let there
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:5652:44"/> be ſuppoſed in the oppoſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> wall a chimney, with a goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> fire in it, about which ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> halfe a dozen women ſit: a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong the reſt, one being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> very old woman, and yet cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in greene (the colour of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> houſe) (like an ape in purple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> telleth a tale to the reſt, liftin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vp her hands as ſhe ſpeaket<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> with ſuch ridiculous and an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticke geſture and action, as be ſitteth a beldame goſſip: wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> upon the whole quire of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> goſſips burſt out into low<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> laughing, and holding thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> hips, with laughter and cough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, make ſuch a confuſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> noiſe, that the crie of <hi>Milo</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the former roome cannot b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> heard. And hence is deriued th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> relation which this Idea hath vnto the former, becauſe they
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:5652:44"/> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re both of them lowd ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing Idea's: though the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>und be a lamentable outcry; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd the latter, a ſound of mirth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd ioy.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="observation">
                  <head>The ninth Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>Men are certainly more anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t then the gods of the heathen: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecauſe men were the makers of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hem.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>This is expreſſible by a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ect Idea; by fancying a ſtatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ie in a purple waſtcoate, to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n the firſt place of the eight <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> (whoſe colour is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urple) faſhioning a marble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mage.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="observation">
                  <head>The tenth Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>The ſnow falling whole, and not
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:5652:45"/> melting as it falleth, is alwayes of a ſix-angled figure; ſetting forth vnto vs the wondrous worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Creator.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>The Idea of this obſeruatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is direct, but in an augmente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> quantitie. For ſince one flak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of ſnow is ſo ſmall, that bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> beſtowed in a memoriall plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> it cannot be ſeene of him tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſtandeth on this ſide the <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitorie:</hi> therefore a great heap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of ſnow is to be placed in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> midſt of the ſtage of the ſecon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> roome of the eight <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> whoſe colour being purple, ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moniſheth that ſome part o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Idea muſt be purple: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> therefore I ſuppoſe a purpl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> pendant to be ſtucke in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> heape of ſnow. The relatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of this Idea to the former, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="81" facs="tcp:5652:45"/> in reſpect of the ſubiect. For each of them hath great ſhew of Art, though this being the worke of God, be ten thouſand times more admirable then the other, which is but the worke of mans hands.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="observation">
                  <head>The eleuenth Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>There are three moſt beautifull mothers of three moſt deformed daughters: Familiaritie, which bringeth forth Contempt; Truth which bringeth foorth Hatred; and Peace, which bringeth forth Sloth.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>I lay it vp by a direct or right Idea in the firſt place of the ninth <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> (whoſe colour is white) after this manner. I ſuppoſe three moſt beautifull
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:5652:46"/> women, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lad in white ſattin, with chapplets of white Roſes vpon their heads, ſitting vpon three low ſtooles, and giuing ſuck to their three daughters, which to looke vpon, are moſt foule and hard fauoured.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="observation">
                  <head>The twelfth Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <p>Aſtrologia Iudiciaria eſt nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiociſſima vanitas.</p> 
                        <bibl>Baſil.</bibl>
                     </q> 
                     <hi>that is,</hi> Iudiciall Aſtrologie is a moſt buſy vanitie.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>The Idea hereof is Relatiue. For it is exemplified by the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Thales</hi> the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher; who taking the altitude of a ſtarre with his Quadrant in the night ſeaſon, taking litle heed vnto his footing, fell in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o a ditch; and was well laught at
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:5652:46"/> by a woman then ſeeing him; and obiecting vnto him his folly, that was ſo curious in looking after things aboue, that he minded not the ditch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. This is to be expreſt in an action vpon the ſecond part of the ſtage belonging to the ninth <hi>Repoſitory;</hi> whoſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour being white, I ſuppoſe his Quadrant to be couered with white paper paſted vpon it. Alſo, that there may be a connexion of this Idea with the former, I conceit it, that the woman runneth to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three women in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer roome, to ſhew them of <hi>Thales</hi> his fall.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="observation">
                  <head>The thirteenth Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation.</head>
                  <list type="syllogism">
                     <item>
                        <q>
                           <p>Whoſoeuer deuoureth that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:5652:47"/> which is conſecrate to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, bringeth deſtruction to his owne family.</p> 
                           <bibl>Prou. <hi>20.25.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                        </q>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <q>
                           <p>But whoſoeuer that ſeizeth into his hands any part of the glebe belonging to the Miniſter, and leaueth it to his poſteritie, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth that which is conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto God.</p> 
                           <bibl>Ezech. <hi>45.4.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                        </q>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>Therefore whoſoeuer ſeizeth any part of the glebe belonging to the Miniſter, and leaueth it to his poſteritie, he bringeth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to his owne family.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>This Syllogiſme is to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed by a compound Idea in the firſt place of the tenth <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> (both the pillars whereof are ſuppoſed to be of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:5652:47"/> gold, according to the laſt rule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f the firſt Chapter.) Firſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ore I ſuppoſe this Syllogiſme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o be fairely written in a white <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>able, foure foot ſquare, whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>order is gilded, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uiſhed into the ſeuerall parts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hereof by ſeuerall ſections, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat is to ſay, into the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tion, Aſſumption and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>luſion; and that the table is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ung vp, vpon the oppoſite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> all in the firſt roome. I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oſe further, that vnderneath his table, cloſe to the oppoſite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> all, there ſitteth in a chaire of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>old, ſome ſacrilegious and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orrupt patron, faſt aſleepe; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hom death comming vnto, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>auing a crowne of gold vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is head, to ſignifie his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>archie, ſtriketh with his dart, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d awakeneth him, ſhewing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:5652:48"/> him the writing ouer his hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> that he may conſider it and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pent, and make a timely reſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tution vnto the Church, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> he damne his owne ſoule, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> bring deſtruction vpon his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mily.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="observation">
                  <head>The fourteenth Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation.</head>
                  <p>Anger is a ſhort madneſſe.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>The Idea of this ſentence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Relatine. For it may fitly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> expreſſed by the hiſtory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.33. who bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> inraged with anger, threw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> iauelin at his ſonne and hei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Ionathan</hi> to kill him. Therfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> I ſuppoſe a man of extraord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nary height, apparelled with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> royall robe of ſtate, hauin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="87" facs="tcp:5652:48"/> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> crowne of pure gold vpon his head, and holding a Iauelin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n his hand, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it vpon a princely throne; and that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>epreſenting <hi>Saul,</hi> vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udden ſtarteth vp, &amp; caſteth it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t a yong man, ſtanding before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>im in the ſame roome, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>elled as befitteth a Prince. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>here needeth no attribution <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f the colour of the <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> this Idea, becauſe <hi>Sauls</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>owne being of gold, is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the proper colour of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nth <hi>Repoſi-torie.</hi> Alſo death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the former place hath a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> owne of gold, as <hi>Saul</hi> alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th in this, and thereby both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s are conioyned.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="observation">
                  <head>The fifteenth Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Magnus Ariſtoteles, trutinando cacumina rerum,</l>
                        <pb n="88" facs="tcp:5652:49"/>
                        <l>In duo diuiſit, quicquid in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> fuit.</l>
                     </q> In Engliſh thus:
<q>
                        <l>Great Ariſtotle weighing well in mind,</l>
                        <l>The eſſence of this vniuerſe; did find,</l>
                        <l>That two things onely were in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> combin'd.</l>
                     </q> that is, Subſtances and Acci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dents.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>This is to be expreſſed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> compound Idea, faining a tab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> to hang vpon the oppoſite wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> foure foote ſquare, the bord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> whereof is ſiluer, (ſo ſuppoſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> becauſe it is placed in the ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenth <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> both who pillars are of ſiluer.) And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in the vpper part of this tabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> are drawne two great paralle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> circles (being the Stenogr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phical
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:5652:49"/> Character of the world) in the midſt whereof is the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of two: and that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath it is drawne a line, and beneath the line, that diſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chon written.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="observation">
                  <head>The ſixteenth Obſeruation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Dic vbi tunc eſſet, cum praeter eum nihil eſſet?</l>
                        <l>Tunc vbi nunc in ſe: quoniam ſibi ſufficit ipſe.</l>
                     </q> In Engliſh thus:
<q>
                        <l>Say, where was God, when ſaue himſelfe, no kind of thing had being?</l>
                        <l>There, where he is, ſtill in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and ſo for euer: ſeeing</l>
                        <l>Himſelfe alone vnto himſelfe is all ſufficient.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>This likewiſe is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by a compound Idea:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:5652:50"/> faining a table to hang vpon the wall of the ſecond place of the eleuenth <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> of the ſame bigneſſe with the former, and in like manner bordered with a ſiluer frame. And that in the vpper part thereof is written in great He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew letters, the name of God <hi>Iehouah,</hi> and nothing elſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſubiect of this Idea is Gods being, when nothing elſe was; with a line drawne vnder it, and thoſe two verſes beneath the line. Both Idea's of this <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> are the ſame in kind, that is to ſay, both Compound, and by this rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fitly ioyned one with an other.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="observation">
                  <head>The ſeuenteenth Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation.</head>
                  <p>Damaſcus in the time of the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:5652:50"/> Prophet Iſai, was the chiefe citie of Syria, as appeareth, Iſai. <hi>7.8.</hi> In the time of our Sauiour Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd long after, Antiochia was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ead citie; but now Aleppo is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hiefeſt citie of Syria.</p>
                  <div type="reposition">
                     <head>The Repoſition.</head>
                     <p>This is to be expreſſed by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>irect Idea, in a contracted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orme. For ſince the Prouince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f Syria (which is the ſubiect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f this ſentence) is ſo great, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat a direct Idea thereof can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ot be contained in a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iall place in full quantitie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>herefore I ſuppoſe the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>te wall of the firſt place of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>welfth <hi>Repoſitories,</hi> to haue a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ge piece of Landtſchape in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ely colours painted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pon: wherein are contained
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:5652:51"/> in a far diſtance one from an other, three goodly cities, ouer which the ſeuerall names of <hi>Damaſcus, Antiochia</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leppo,</hi> are written in ſeuerall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>partements limited by black lines very big, becauſe blacke is the colour of this <hi>Repoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But it is not neceſſary that I ſhould proceed any further, in giuing more examples, becauſe by that which hath already bin deliuered, it is euident enough with what Idea euery thing memorable is to be expreſſed, and in what place to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed. And now, if you ſhall trie with your ſelfe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you can repeate ouer al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Idea's in their order, with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out ſight of the booke, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> are contained in this Chapter
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:5652:51"/> ſo that you throughly well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what you haue read; I doubt not but you wil freely confeſſe, that there is great cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie in this Art.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of the Anomaly of Repoſition.</head>
               <p>THere is but one Anomaly or irregularitie in laying vp Idea's: that is to ſay, when in ſtead of a fained Repoſitory; a true place really ſeene with our eyes is vſed, This Anomaly is admitted vpon two occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons offered.</p>
               <p>Firſt, when the thing it ſelfe is beſtowed really in ſome place, to be, as it were, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall Idea of it ſelfe. As if
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:5652:52"/> a ſcholler ſitting in his ſtody, lighteth vpon a booke, one of whoſe ſheets is ſowne out of order, and purpoſeth to haue it that day mended; let him lay it downe then at the doore of his ſtudy, that when he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth, he may by the ſight thereof be put in mind to take it with him, and ſo to put it forth to mending.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when preſently after we haue layd vp the Idea in our mind, we muſt put it out againe. As for example: if a man be talking with a rich man, and whiles he is in ſpeech with him, it commeth into his mind, to ſpeake vnto him in the behalfe of a poore neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of his, the rich mans tenant: let him then ſuppoſe that neighbour of his to be
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:5652:52"/> there preſent, ſtanding or ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in ſome place, which his eye hath deſigned, and that he ſtandeth there ſtill in ſight, till he be entred into talke concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him. Or, if againe before he part from him, it commeth into his mind to buy wood of him; and that becauſe they are yet ſtill in ſad talke vpon other matters, time ſerueth him not to ſpeake of it; let him then imagine himſelfe to ſee a ſmall ſtacke or pile of wood, in ſome certaine place which he deſigneth with his eyes, and keepe ſtill in mind what Idea he hath there placed, that he may ſpeake of it when he ſeeth his time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:5652:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Of Depoſition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HItherunto I haue ſpoken onely of the firſt part of the Art of Memory, called Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſition: it remaineth to ſpeake ſomewhat concerning the ſecond part, called Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
               <p>Depoſition is, whereby things before committed to memory, are called to minde againe, and either committed to writing, or otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched, that ſo it may be put out of our mind: and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall places after ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the <hi>Idea's</hi> being left emptie, may be the fitter to receiue new <hi>Idea's</hi> into them.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:5652:53"/>
               <p>This depoſition or putting things out of mind, muſt be vndertaken as ſoone as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently we can; that the minde may not be charged with the burthen of them longer then needs muſt; and that we may the ſooner call them to mind, ſeeing they were but a little before layd vp in our remembrance. But if it falleth out, that when we go about to call to mind any thing that was before commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to memory, the Idea thereof being more negligently layd vp, appeareth not; then we muſt aſſay to call it to minde, by following this courſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is knowne for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, that euery Idea which lyeth hid, hath in ſome part the colour of the <hi>Repoſitorie</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:5652:54"/> attributed vnto it; we muſt therefore firſt enquire, in what maner the colour of the <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie</hi> was aſcribed vnto it. For by this very conſideration commonly all <hi>Idea's</hi> that are obſcure, are brought forth to light.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if the Idea will not by this meanes be called to mind, then next we muſt trie, whether we can bring it into remembrance, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation which it had vnto the other Idea placed in the ſame <hi>Repoſitorie,</hi> in reſpect of the quantitie, ſituation, ſubiect, kind, or of the action of the latter Idea transferred vnto the former. For one Idea of the <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> being certainely knowne, will not ſuffer the other to lie hidden, but by the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:5652:54"/> mutuall relation of them one to another (whereby they are as it were chained together) it ſhall be compelled to come forth, except the Repoſition hath beene too ſlothfull.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if neither by this meanes, we can bring the Idea to remembrance, we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke vs of what kind it was, (that is, whether it were a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Idea, a Relatiue, Subditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, or compound Idea,) or in what quantitie it was layd vp, (that is, in an equall, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, or contracted quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,) or what poſition or ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it had, (that is, whether it was placed vpon the wall, vpon a table, vpon a cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord or ſhelfe, vpon the ſtage, or vnderneath it:) or laſtly, whether it had any motion
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:5652:55"/> or ſound aſcribed vnto it. For by ſuch queſtions the Idea is often found out.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, if we know, that the Idea which we ſeeke, was indeed a Scriptile Idea; but what the writing it ſelfe was, we haue forgotten: then we muſt ſearch it out, by bethink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs of the bigneſſe of the table, whether it were one foote and an halfe broade, for three foote broade, or of a bigger ſize, that hereby we may know, whether it were the Idea of a ſingle word, Quotation, Phraſe, ſhort Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or long. If it be found to be a long ſentence, then we are to examine the faſhion and manner of writing it; that ſo we may come to know, what kinde of ſentence it was that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:5652:55"/> we ſeeke for; as that it was a Diſtribution, a Syllogiſme, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſwer of ſome obiection, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imilitude, or other kind of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entence, diſtinguiſhable by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he parts thereof. Now if by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his meanes we find what kind of Scriptile Idea that was which now lyeth hid, as that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was a Quotation, ſhort ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence, Syllogiſme, ſimilitude, &amp;c. but yet we know not in particular any word thereof; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen we muſt ſeeke out the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hiefe word of the <hi>Idea,</hi> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alling to minde, if we can, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he firſt letter thereof; which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to be found out by repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing the Alphabet in order, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd well expending and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what letter ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mind will faſten vpon. For it will certainly faſten vpon the right
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:5652:56"/> letter, if a blameable repoſition hath not gone before. Now when we haue found out the firſt letter, then we muſt apply the other letters of the Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet that will follow that better thereunto, to find what is the ſecond letter; and when we haue the two firſt letters, it is an eaſie matter by the length of the word, the tranſcenden<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cies therein, and the two firſt letters, to finde out the whole firſt word, and thereby to come to the knowledge of the ſentence.</p>
               <p>To conclude, if by none of theſe meanes you can find out the <hi>Idea</hi> which you ſeeke for, let it paſſe, and trouble not your ſelfe any further a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſearch of it. For if you reade or heare the ſame
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:5652:56"/> word ſpoken by any the ſame day, or the next day after, it is very likely that the whole ſentence will come then to memorie. For as a booke, which a man hath negligently beſtowed in his ſtudie, is not peraduenture found when he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeketh it, though he remoue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he moſt of his bookes in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tudie; when notwithſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fterwards, taking foorth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooke next it, he findeth that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſo which before was miſſing: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſometimes it commeth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſe, that a ſentence which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath beene careleſly commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to memorie, cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound when it is ſought for; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich notwithſtanding when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e notion lying next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o it in the ſtore-houſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emorie is called foorth, it
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:5652:57"/> ſelfe alſo will come to mind therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5652:57"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
